Guide to the R.A. (Roy Austin) Davidson papers AD.MC.083
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
R.A. (Roy Austin) Davidson papers
1918-1921, 1943
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Davidson, R.A. (Roy A.), 1886-1980
AD.MC.083
0.10 Linear Feet in 17 file folders.
Report, map, and correspondence, related to the reconnaissance mission led by Captain R.A. Davidson, of the British Army, to determine the extent of arms smuggling from the Arabian Peninsula into Egypt in 1919. The collection also includes a separate report authored by Davidson, dating from 1917, pertaining to the cultivation of barley in Lower Egypt, and documents from the British Army in World War II, related to Davidson's activities in recruitment in northwestern England.
Content Description
The R.A. Davidson papers consist of a report, and supporting documentation, which resulted from a reconnaissance mission to survey the Red Sea coast of Egypt, in order to determine whether locations along the coast were being used for arms smuggling from the Arabian Peninsula. In addition to Davidson's report, an additional report he compiled in 1917, describing the conditions for the cultivation of barley in the coastal region of northwest Egypt, is also included with these papers.
The occasion for the reconnaissance mission, and the resulting report compiled by Captain Davidson, was the suspicion that after the end of World War I, hostile elements were smuggling weapons from the Arabian Peninsula to the Red Sea coast of Egypt, where they were then collected and distributed inland. According to orders issued by A.W. Keown-Boyd, Oriental Secretary to the High Commissioner of Egypt, Edmund Allenby, Davidson and his team were to conduct a thorough survey of the Red Sea coastline, from the Gulf of Suez to the border between Sudan and Eritrea, in order to document and assess the conditions and forces needed to intercept such smugglers. Keown-Boyd suggested that a combination of sea planes, camel patrols, and car patrols might be necessary, and that such a reconnaissance mission could establish which of these would be most effective, and how many of such forces would be required.
According to Davidson's diary, included in his report, the group departed Cairo for Suez on 30 June 1919, and then boarded the S.S. Aida, which left on 3 July. The survey of the coastline included ports such as Hurghada, Sharm el-Sheikh, Port Sudan, and Suakin, with party members often disembarking to explore the surrounding areas by car, sometimes driving as far as Qena, on the Nile River, before returning to the coast. The group returned to Suez on 7 August.
Davidson's report concluded that there was no evidence of any arms smuggling to be found at that time, but he recommended that the area be patrolled by camel corps, with light car patrols being used further inland, as a second line of patrol, and that dhow traffic be restricted to specially designated ports. The most extensive portion of the report consists of a detailed description of the ports and anchorages along the coast (pages 48-71), as well as a separate appendix describing roads and the coastline (pages 34-47). In addition, attached lists of dhows that arrived at specific ports between 1917 and 1919 was used by Davidson as a means of recommending measures to be taken to control dhow traffic.
Davidson's report consists of a copy of the orders, his summary, and then appendices covering specific topics of the survey, and a concluding diary for the expedition. One missing segment that he had listed in the table of contents was Appendix A.12, covering water supplies, and consisting of 18 pages of text. In a letter of 15 June 1921 to "Hope" (last name unknown), Davidson mentioned that this section was missing from this copy of the report, as it was requested by the "F.D.A. and Mines Department of Egypt," and as he had the only copy of that text, he left that with them before departing Egypt. The original folder in which the report was bound also contains a folded map of the Red Sea coast of Egypt, which was pasted to the inside rear cover of the folder, and has been kept attached to it.
He notes in that same letter that he made 8 copies of the report for General Headquarters, submitting the original to General Lord Allenby, the High Commissioner for Egypt. In the same letter, he references the "Notes on Barley Growing in the Coastal Belt of Northwest Egypt," leading to the likelihood that both reports, and the related correspondence, were kept in the possession of "Hope" and may have been handed down from her to others over the decades. Loose letters and documents that were filed in the report included correspondence to Davidson summoning him to a meeting at the Savoy Hotel in Cairo to discuss the planned mission, and a precis of the proceedings of that meeting.
In addition to the reports and documents dating from the period of Davidson's service in Egypt, the collection also contains a separate file of documents from 1943, when Davidson was serving as a Quartering Commandant in the Lancashire and Border District of the British Army, and appears to have participated in the process of calling up officers to serve in newly occupied areas, most likely in North Africa.
Biographical note
R.A. (Roy Austin) Davidson (1886-1980) was an officer in the British Army, with first the Denbigh Hussars Yeomanry, and later the 24th Regiment of the Royal Welsh Fusiliers.
Prior to the outbreak of World War I, he was a non-commissioned officer in the Denbigh Hussars, and was commissioned as a 2nd Lieutenant in May 1915, and sent with his unit to Egypt in March 1916, where he subsequently served in the Light Car Patrols. In March 1917, he was awareded the Military Cross for his actions at the battle of Siwa Oasis, where his citation stated that "he showed great coolness and resource getting his patrol over almost impossible ground" while he "inflicted considerable casualties on the retreating enemy." In July 1918 he was promoted to the rank of acting Captain, and later Captain. Following the armistice, he was tasked by the High Commissioner for Egypt, Lord Allenby, to conduct a reconnaissance survey of the Red Sea coast of Egypt, in order to gain information that could be useful in combatting arms smuggling.
Following the reconnaissance mission, he appeared to have returned to England in September 1919, settling in Cheshire, and later in Preston, Lancashire. During the inter-war years, he worked as a chartered land agent, managing large agricultural estates in northwestern England. Documents in this collection show that he may have been involved in the recruitment of officers to serve as administrators in newly occupied territories overseas, although it is unclear whether he applied for such a position or not. Other records show that he was listed as a Local Lieutenant Colonel in the Army List of 1945.
In later years, Davidson lived in Beaumaris, on the island of Anglesey, in Wales, where he died in 1980.
Sources:
"The Denbighshire Hussars," [website], https://www.paoyeomanry.org.uk/DenbighYeo24Btn.htm, accessed in August 2022.
"The Great War (1914-1918) Forum," website, and discussion regarding Denbigh Hussars Yeomanry, 2010: https://www.greatwarforum.org/topic/153404-denbigh-hussars-yeomanry/, accessed August 2022
Williams, Claud H. "Light Car Patrols 1916-1919: War and exploration in Egypt and Libya with the Model T Ford," edited and with an introduction by Russell McGuirk (London: Silphium Press; Royal Geographical Society, 2013).
Arrangement
The R.A. Davidson papers are arranged in two series, in chronological order.
Conditions governing access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, November 2019.
World War, 1914-1918 -- Campaigns -- Egypt; Red Sea Coast (Egypt); Egypt -- History -- British occupation, 1882-1936; Illegal arms transfers -- Egypt; Barley -- Breeding -- Egypt
- Report: "Report of a Reconnaissance of the Red Sea Coast, and means suggested for the prevention of illicit traffic in arms," compiled by Captain R.A. Davidson, undated, approximately August 1919
  - Copy of orders and summary of report (pages 1-7) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appendix A.1: Description of ports, lists of dhows arriving and departing from ports (pages 8-12) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appendix A.2 and A.3: Seaplanes, Camel corps (pages 13-20) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appendix A.4 - A.6: Intercommunications, Landing of arms, potential sites (pages 21-25) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appendix A.7 - A.9: Light car patrols, sloops, motor boats (pages 26-33) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Appendix A.10]: Description of roads and coastline (pages 34-47) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appendix A.11: Description of ports and anchorages (pages 48-71) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Diary (pages 91-93) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Folder cover with folding map affixed to inside back cover (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Related documents, 1917-1921, 1943
  - Report (manuscript): "Notes on Barley Growing in the Coastal Belt of North West Egypt," with letter of recipient of copy of report, November 1917 - January 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence pertaining to reconnaissance mission, June 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Precis of Proceedings of Conference, Savoy Hotel, Cairo, 14 June 1919 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum regarding proposed reconnaissance mission, from Major W.D. Long to Major N.S. MacDonnell, 21 June 1919 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Orders to Captain R.A. Davidson from A.W. Keown-Boyd, undated, likely June 1919 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letter of appreciation for Davidson's report, from General Headquarters, Egyptian Expeditionary Force, 4 September 1919 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter to Hope, last name unknown, 15 June 1921 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Recruitment of officers, British defence forces, Lancashire and Border District, May - July 1943 (Box 1, Folder 17)